welcome to voices with verveiki
i'm joined with then greg he's one of my
former students and
a current colleague we are working on a
book together
and he is daniel is here to talk to us
uh today about some work he's doing on
in terms of
an artist collective and an alternative
reality
and although that sounds a little bit
off topic it's actually
central centrally on topic because
daniel's main
uh goal in all of this is to uh
create a you know a
widely shareable way in which people can
bridge between science and spirituality
which of course is the main purview of
voices with for vague so
welcome daniel hi yeah thanks for having
me i'm really excited to talk about this
i've had a lot of
intellectual developments um since i
just recently graduated
i've had a bit of a return to the uh
artist identity that
i kind of turned away from when i was
doing my undergrad i really bought
deeply into this sort of academic and
scientific side of things i was like i'm
gonna
buckle down and be a researcher and all
of that but
a few existential transformations later
and i'm like wait you know maybe there
are more fun and playful ways to
accomplish the same kinds of things
and along with that i think this sort of
more playful mode of engagement with
reality is perhaps
um what we need and something that the
scientific mode on its own simply can't
give us because of the very conservative
standards
of um judgment and decision making that
are inherent to the scientific process
so i take it i mean and you know
obviously you and i are working together
but i take it that this
what you want to talk about would be a
significant instance of what i've been
talking about when i talk about serious
play
yeah yeah yeah yeah exactly um
serious play i think that's like a
really great way that's always stood out
to me as like a really good way to talk
about like what's going on with
um a religious uh community right
there's this kind of reality this
mystical spiritual reality
that is concentrated in the temple or in
the church and you know in heinekerian
terms the purpose of the temple is to
open up a world
um predicated upon these uh more
spiritualistic
modes of experience and along line with
the book that we're writing um that
spiritual dimension of experiences
is critical for actually um enabling an
authentic
dialogue with not only other people but
with reality
um and we can judge the efficacy of that
dialogue not in terms of the
propositions that we generate about it
but in how well we can relate to others
how well we can relate to the natural
world
and how sustainable that relation is
over a long period of time
so so the touchstone is something more
like
wisdom broadly construed rather than the
acquisition of sort of theoretical
knowledge
yes definitely and along with the wisdom
stuff something that i'm really trying
to add um
in this book is the importance of the
idea of divine wisdom which kind of got
like thrown out um
which i think is kind of throwing out
the baby with the bath water we got rid
of the god thing and then we also
thought oh
this whole system's involving wisdom we
can probably throw that out too
and i think that's really missing from
the psychological research into wisdom
right um because if you look at just the
individual character traits and
personality traits
uh things like um openness to experience
or um you know grossman talks about
emotional complexity being really
important and making decisions wisely
those kinds of things they don't really
distinguish the sage from
um somebody who is perhaps a little bit
more nefarious but has like really good
social skills
for example right right right yeah so i
think this
the notion of divine wisdom is really
important um and the
notion traditionally has been that there
is some kind of creative force
emanating into our reality um starting
in god flowing through the angels
and then entering into the hearts of the
community um
in christianity that's often been
through the hierarchy of the church it
concentrates
the um the creative force of god
um through that hierarchical structure
and brings everybody
into this sort of systems involving
world involving
um form of wisdom so that brings in
something and
you know and it's relevant to the book
we're writing and it's been sort of my
concern with
i mean i was i was involved with igor
igor grossman
in uh the wisdom consensus paper and i
i'm how did that work i think there's an
excellent work
that was done there but i do think that
yeah this notion of of self
transcendence
and its attendant notion because i think
they belong together uh
of uh you know communitas with others
it's not those are not yet finding a
proper home
uh within the current scientific
discussion of wisdom
yeah i definitely agree and in order to
get that um
you do have to have a picture of like
what the wise community looks like
right and and you know for that i really
like the
the theory of iambicus iambicus is like
the most righteous of all neoplatonists
he's like a really down-to-earth guy
i definitely think that's really well
that's what you mean by righteous uh you
have to remember daniel i'm older than
you so righteous carries a different
meaning
for me right i mean he's like super cool
and he's on to some good stuff
right okay go ahead so let me um
let me just like flash out these uh
projects that i want to talk about
because what i really want to get out of
this um
interaction is twofold so on one side i
want to
broadcast these ideas to people because
i need to start recruiting people
to be doing a lot of work that i simply
can't do on my own yes i need to
establish the kind of wise community
that i'm seeking to implement
and secondly i think you know it's been
a long time since we've had a
conversation and i think that you'll
have some really good input for how to
effectively implement this so
i also want to get a little bit more
insight into how to
effectively carry this out from you as
well that that'd be great i mean i
um i consider myself a dedicated novice
to this project of
community building i've been engaging in
it for a couple i guess
close to a year and a half now um
outside of university and of course
i've been engaging in it uh within the
university of the cogside community for
a couple of decades
but that was a very special kind of
community an academic community
this broader kind of community that you
and i are talking about uh has of course
uh unique and different features that
make it especially challenging
um so yeah i'm happy to discuss that but
let's let's discuss the first thing
let's discuss these projects
and how they involve serious play uh the
cultivation of wisdom the affording of
self-transcendence and communitas so
let's
start explaining them and how they
uh fulfill these functions and why they
might contribute to
human flourishing in some fashion sure
so i'll start with the art collective
side of it i think that's important for
grounding it
i i just have some working titles right
now but i think the working titles will
give you
a bit of insight into where i'm going
with this so what i want to call it
right now is harmonia and then subtitle
and an active vision collective oh
that's nice
so harmonia is based on the idea um in
the ancient world and in the renaissance
of the harmony of the spheres
right so it was generally well um
well understood that music was a
product of motion the vibration of
strings would move the air and then that
movement would initiate a musical
experience upon the meeting of that
movement
in our sensory apparatus now
the ancient thinkers also looked up at
the stars and saw that they were in
constant motion
and they reasoned that if motion was the
source of music and if the heavens were
in motion
then there would also be some kind of
heavenly divine music
which had a state of harmony a state of
divine harmony
everything's working in order right
harmony is when things are complementary
they work with each other in cohesion to
create a state of beauty
and a state of harmony and if you look
at the
function of the mystical experience
according to like platinus and iamblicus
and these other neoplatonists
what is happening is a harmonization of
the soul all of the parts of the soul
are coming to operate in
a harmonious unity and as a part of that
harmonious unity you get the powers of
agency
and you also get the power of god's
divine providence
you get to participate in the creative
force of god
um so that's something that i think is
uh really important i think
it's you could say something more of a
metaphorical lens but i think that that
metaphor enables
a really profound relationship with
reality
if you understand the universe as music
and harmony compared to
mechanism and logic you get very
different relationships out of reality
so part of this art collective and the
projects that i'm going to be running
with it are meant to educate people
into a universe which is predicated on
the metaphors of music
harmony and the living being compared to
the
more recent world view in which we've
been situated in the one
dominated by technology and logic and
formal systems all of those kinds of
things
so the inactive vision part of it um
refers of course to an active cognitive
science
the idea that an organism has the kind
of conscious experience that it does
because of how it learns to negotiate
its embodied relationships with the
world
right by acting in the world it carves
out its conscious experience
right right and so i think that we've
also been
uh missing out on an important kind of
knowledge right this kind of
participatory knowledge
yep that you like to talk about so much
and so
the inactive vision i think is something
like this participatory kind of
knowledge that being in a transformative
space with um art and play and metaphor
it will enable people not to necessarily
grasp propositions but to
experience the embodied vision of what
it's like to inhabit
a particular kind of world in order to
take that world out into the world
beyond which is you know exactly how
you've described
uh religious practices in the past right
so
um it sounds like and that would make
sense to me
it sounds like this is making use of the
arguments i've sort of drawn from
l.a paul and agnes callard about
you know the the aspirational project
the kind of knowing that it involves a
transformation of your existential modes
a transformation of your participatory
knowing so you
it's not that you come to possess or
have new propositions you come to be
a different kind of agent in a different
kind of arena is that a fair way of
putting it yeah yeah
absolutely um radical arena
transformation is precisely the kind of
thing i'm going for
so it would be also therefore radical
agency transformation too wouldn't it
uh yes yes yes yeah okay
and so that would also be so i i i mean
this sounds like
uh a way of really uh
doing a couple of things deepening the
sense of the being mode and the
developmental aspiration they're in
uh but it also affords people
playing in this alternative reality if
i'll put it that way or
augment it i sometimes call it the trans
world where i'm using
a token's notion of fantasy not as an uh
an escapist other world but as a
different way of returning and seeing
this world
or something like that but the idea of
a serious play is um that it allows you
to get a participatory and perspectival
taste of that other
world without having gone over into a
full-blown
sort of abandonment of everything that
you have here is that is that the idea
yeah yeah absolutely and i'll clarify
exactly
the project that is going to carry this
out in a moment but i also wanted to
mention this thing about the
transformative experience paradox right
which i'm sure people who listen to this
are very familiar with the problem that
wow how do i become that other person
that i am not because my preferences are
not even those person's preferences i
don't even know how to relate to that
future character
right exactly so that problem has been
solved in the past by having a
community of people who are sustaining a
vision of life that you can then bind
yourself to
yes yes right the buddhist community the
christian community those are places
that you can go
to find the answer to who that you you
should become
actually is and what that looks like so
within our culture we actually i think
need to have
some kind of space some kind of
situational arena
that solves the problem of the
transformative experience paradox
for people we have to have that answer
available so that when people
experience deep dissatisfaction and they
feel that
call to go on what might be called the
enlightenment journey by diving into
transformative states of consciousness
trying to become wise trying to become
satisfied to overcome suffering
that's an impossible task or at least a
near impossible
task to do on your own and you know the
theravadan buddhists they
would claim for example that the only
true buddha is the one who initiates
this kind of
novel practice this kind of novel way of
life which is a really
tall order to expect of anybody i think
it is like a wise thing to say well you
know we have people who can
set this vision for life and then we
have a community of practice
who binds themselves to this vision it's
like a distributed
computation uh solution to the
transformative experience problem
so so uh i mean uh one
answer that i sometimes get when i talk
about this with people is they say well
we already have
i don't know we already have sort of a a
socially uh
acceptable way in which people go and
experience this kind of serious play
to engage in this kind of transformation
it's called therapy and people go and
see
therapists and how they undergo so are
you just proposing i know you're not so
this is
a bit of a softball question but it's
it's an invitation question you're not
just proposing some kind of
art therapy you're proposing something
greater than that right
something far greater than that because
therapy is highly individualistic and
all that it can do
is bind you to the way that things are
now
but the way that things are now are
instrumental in
everybody's suffering um the quote
that's always stuck with me from like
my early days as a psychedelic
enthusiast is the quote by krishnamurti
which goes
it's no measure of health to be well
adjusted to a profoundly sick society
right right and i think therapy is great
and i think that psychedelic therapy is
also an amazing and wonderful thing
but we have to look at transformative
experience
and the project of wisdom aspiration
in a way that i think parallels how we
can talk about drug policy for example
you can have um
there's a number of different strategies
you can have you can have a harm
reduction strategy for example
which seeks to simply remove the harms
from drug use
or you can have a benefit maximization
strategy which recognizes that things
like psychedelics or other substances
are radically profound and powerful
and then looks to
integrate those kinds of things into our
culture in a way that maximizes the
benefits
safely and rationally and so i think
that thing kind of goes
also just for transformations of self
and transformations of consciousness in
general
and i very much see one-on-one therapy
as something that
is just incapable of maximizing the
benefits of transformative experience
compared to something that is more
culturally relevant and culturally
active
which is why i think that an art
collective is necessary because we need
to start informing the narrative
structures at play in our reality
if we are to um engage in the sort of
broad
world transformation that will just
produce happier people by
a result of being a better world okay
that was very well said
i know that was very well said uh you're
very you're uh
being quite eloquent today which is very
enjoyable thank
thank you writing this book has been
helping that clarity a lot
well i'm glad i'm glad to hear that um
so um
i should mention for those of you who
are interested in the book daniel and i
have done a previous
video where we talk about the book and
so if you want to go and check that out
i'll put a link in this video to that
previous video so we won't just keep
alluding to this book and you have no no
no idea what we're talking about but now
let's turn to
the more specific you know proposals
that you have
so please okay so
here's here's what i think the religion
that's not a religion
requires i think this is a necessary
element
so for a while i had been trying to plan
this project trying to conceive of it
um and i've been thinking in like very
serious terms you know like we have to
have like a building and it has to like
have meditation teachers and we have to
like teach people philosophy and all of
this stuff but then
i was i was talking to someone um i know
you've been on their podcast
tim from from voice club oh tim edelman
yeah
i was having a conversation with him and
he was like questioning me about well
is this kind of thing like very viable
if we need social distancing measures
and just that was enough to like click
in my head i was like holy crap
i could make this a game i could make
an online run alternate reality game
that has occasional in-person activities
but it has resiliency um against you
know perhaps a second wave of covet or
some other future issue that might
emerge however long down the road um
to run this as kind of a decentralized
platform
and so as i got thinking about how i
could run that i came up with the idea
for the great
awakening and so the great awakening is
the name of this game
um i think it's very culturally apropos
because that's the hashtag that you see
always um on this q a narrative stuff
right
this very interesting and intricate kind
of psycho-spiritual warfare that people
are engaged with
you know the deep state against
everybody else
it's a bizarre thing we can start
talking about it but i think that
the way that people make meaning is
already you know as you say it's like an
agent arena relationship thing going on
i think that we can articulate
consciousness in general
as a process of augmented reality game
generation
and then if we did something like that
we'd probably all be a little bit better
off because we're all just playing games
at the end of the day
how seriously we take those games
depends on the parameters of the game
and the games that we make sense of
determine our action they determine our
relationship to the world
so in the question of what is the best
game that we can play i thought that we
probably need to really
clearly get some alternative game out
there that can
interface with people's meaning making
powers
and to draw them out of this descent
into self-deception and foolishness
and and bind them to um a cultural hyper
object that is in their better interest
right right so the
so can i ask a question so yeah yeah
that this game is not meant to exclude
people undertaking the task of training
skills of mindfulness or rationality
or anything like that that's not what
because what you might what you said
might have been taken to convey that no
actually that stuff is a part of it
right right so let me lay out what it's
going to look like so
basically it's a live-action role-play
secret society simulator
right okay larps yeah yeah
and so what happens is you um you
actually let me start with the sort of
cosmic narrative in which it's situated
right okay
so there's a god his name is anthem he
is the god of stories and time
because that is the his name is a play
on the structure of stories and then and
then and then and then
right right and and so this is one of
the the primordial old gods
so if we think back to like uh hp
lovecraft's cosmos he has like the
um you know the outer ones who are like
massive forces of chaos and
incomprehensible cosmic power
and and then is one of those but
because it's so fundamental to change
into time
and then permeates everything and so
he's a force that can become
personal and can address us as an
individual
right okay and especially because human
beings we have such a
profound capacity for storytelling and
for story generation and then is
particularly close with us
because we kind of maximize that latent
power for creation within the and then
structure of reality
right right right so and that is very
deeply concerned
about the narrative structures that are
at play in our reality
and building on um federico campania's
technique and magic i'm calling
the deity that governs the current
narrative structure is technic
right right so technic he likes
production and he likes capital
accumulation
he tries to reduce everything into a
productive analytical series
formal systems are the only things that
are allowed to exist in that kind of
reality system
and the necessary end of that is our
annihilation the
incorporation of everything into this
flat
ontology of serial production
right right right so and that is
concerned because he doesn't want us to
die he's very fond of us because we can
like give him
greater and more interesting things to
do and so what he does is he
sets up a secret society called the
academy for existential excellence
and his task is to
incorporate people into a
a new way of being a new kind of
narrative structure that can then
replace and topple
uh the old one uh governed by technic
which is leading to our demise
and so as a part of the existential x um
the economy for existential excellence
um it'll be about a three-month journey
and in the first month you're doing
mostly
um coursework and wisdom-based practices
um so you know meditation um we could do
horses and logic
um i'm getting alex jetovic who just
finished his phd
uh to do a course on uh natural agency
and the metaphor of the living being
right right as like a better way to
understand evolution and agency
so there'll be some good rigorous cog
sci stuff in there but it'll all be
embedded within this playful narrative
um which will also have some
kind of semi-fictional content that'll
be entertaining and educate you into the
history and the story of this particular
narrative
right and after that first month and a
half though things start to get weird
because the alternate reality that and
then is trying to get us to
move towards is starting to phase into
our reality
the members of the academy are called
synthesis i really like synthesizers as
a metaphor for consciousness
um the synthesizer is like your basic
dynamical system it has like a space of
all possible sound
and then with different um oscillators
and um effects
you like change it so that it has a
different kind of outcome
right so i think that the individual
consciousness is kind of like a
synthesizer in that respect we can like
apply these warps and oscillations to it
to like change the output
and so you learn the skills of synthesis
which is basically a skill of like magic
and channeling and the point
um of this educational system is to have
a whole set of minds synthesizing new
beings and new
cultural entities into reality and so as
a part of that
once enough power has been built built
up by people doing these practices and
congregating and maybe
you know performing some ritualistic
acts etc um
then then it gets interesting because
that alternate timeline that we're
trying to
coordinate ourselves with starts phasing
into reality so there's a number of
immersive theater shows which will allow
people to go and visit
and participate in this alternate
reality that we could have been living
in now if only we had done things
differently a few hundred years ago
but that we can match ourselves up with
down the road if only we engage in this
process of synthesis effectively
right and at the end there will be this
grand ritual
initiation um i have an art collective
called komatica they're from the uk um
they're also
networked with the imperial college
people uh researching psychedelics
to build um transformative profoundly
altering
um ritualistic performance experiences
right
so i've been talking to them about
having some kind of grand initiation at
the end which will then
make you sort of a permanent member of
this community of the academy
that's cool that's what so it sounds
like something like
the eleusian mysteries at the end that
they had in the
hellenic culture yeah yeah it's very
very mystery school vibe there's a
number of um
you know secrets that have to be
initiated in lots of symbols that'll be
primed throughout the experience that
um will take a central role in that
uh final ritual culmination
so what can there's lots of practical
questions but
maybe a more high-level question first
what connection is there between
um the game and
um and what you're calling the art
collective like what's that what's the
relationship there
so the art collective is the thing that
is going to implement and build the game
i see i see it's also going to be
something that
i take at homes the final stage of the
initiation
sort of practice that um is
is that is that is that like they're
going to help uh create that space in
which that occurs
yeah yeah absolutely so you know i need
to establish an art collective because i
need a number of people with like
skills um i need people for doing like
set design and stage design
uh i need people to help me produce
video content for the online courses and
all of this
um so the the collective will be the
community of people that are responsible
for constructing and building and then
carrying out the game
you're also i guess going to need people
who are good at programming
and video game production and things
like that as well um well there's not
going to be really much on the
you know it's an alternate reality game
but that doesn't mean that there's like
virtual reality stuff necessarily um
it'll be
kind of like a live action role play um
so so
yeah right right right okay so most of
it is taking place
in sort of the imaginal space a lot of
it yeah
and then there will be um there's like
an online platform called mighty
networks that i want to run it off it
allows you to have a social network that
also
allows you to run courses off of so
that's the online platform that i want
to use and then it'll be
you know you go on coursera you find um
online courses it'll look very similar
to that
but it'll all be sort of networked in
with this larger narrative structure
right and so the goal is that
people will come out of this in
something
something analogous to having belonged
to a church or to a temple
or something like that or a mosque for
an extended period of time
yeah yeah exactly that's cool
and and who's gonna like moderate it
uh because i can i can also imagine
that this kind of game will attract
attention from
uh bad faith players who don't want it
to succeed
um for various nefarious reasons
right that is possible there's a lot of
logistical things that i i need to
work out and that is for sure right now
i'm very much in the in the phase of
like idea generation and story
generations i've been focusing mostly on
on world building
right um for moderation the the
particular theater shows that i've come
up with
which i don't want to share because you
know spoilers would kind of ruin the
effect of the game
right um i have ways of incorporating
people who are like part of the game
uh as sort of in situation
moderators to kind of control moments
like that right
so like i said so this is very much the
live action the larping
right um so are you after are you after
something like
uh what happens in jeep form are you
after the bleed phenomena
where the line between the play
environment and
and the everyday world bleeds and you
start to get a transformative
relationship between them is that
is bleed sort of the goal that is being
saw yes
absolutely while it is situated in a
playful context i do think that
the metaphor of life and music
are much better ways for modeling
reality especially if we're looking at
how we develop the right kinds of
participatory relationships with reality
so i think that you know not only are
they this is is this the optimal
framework in terms of it promoting the
best kind of relationship i also think
that it's like
a lot more true than a strictly
mechanistic view
and so you can look at like for example
the work of dennis walsh and lee smallin
roberto unger
there's numerous people coming out now
i'm trying to resurrect this idea that
the cosmos is something more like an
organism in how it
evolves and changes yes and how the
process of creation carries out
um yeah so yeah it's playful but it's
also like i think that this kind of
reality is like literally true at least
those
fundamental propositions that it's um
grounded upon
so it's kind of uh a white hedian
version of neoplatonism
then i i think you'll have to elaborate
that reference for me
uh so uh you know how
whitehead basically tried to bring back
you know
organic an organic model um
on organic metaphysics um in
but in a way that was very uh
neoplatonic
but he tried to do it in a way that
would
ultimately be consonant with two
projects one was what he called religion
in the making
the title of one of his books and the
other project was
getting uh get and these two projects
are supposed to be linked getting us
into a metaphysics that is also um
gives us a better way of interpreting
and understanding our science
but interpreting and understanding it in
a way that is consonant with the
religion
in the making um that's that's very much
his project
yeah yeah that sounds just about right
that's interesting i've been putting off
reading whitehead for a while maybe
that's been a mistake
i would do not start with process in
reality which is one of the hardest
books to read
um you might want the book that might be
uh the two books that would be relevant
to your project might be
um i think science and education maybe
or at least
um a really good book would probably be
religion in the making
oh yeah yeah that sounds about right
excellent i've also come across a recent
um thing sent by my friend simon cook
there was this guy in like the early
20th century who was a part of the
sort of socialist movements in russia he
was one of the ones who got sort of
you know excommunicated and not taken
seriously but
he had this project called god building
and i was like amazed it seemed like
very much similar to like what you're
trying to do what i'm trying to do
um and the idea was to like look at how
religion was positive
and to construct a religion that would
best meet the needs of a society that
could meet everybody's needs who is this
theorist his name is luna charsky
i'd like to know more about it so i'll
thank simon for passing that on
uh but yeah if you i'd like to know if
you could send me some links about it
or what anything simon sent you on it i
would appreciate that
yeah there's one good paper um there's
unfortunately not a lot of his books
still left out because he was kind of
like forgotten about
um i think maybe he was a bit too kind
for to religion for the the soviets to
really
latch on to so there's one paper and
he's like yeah i just got like the first
like really good translation all of the
other copies are like you know too
brittle to be
scanned and so there's no actual direct
copies of his book that can be read
in like um an english or um
other more central european language but
uh that paper does a really good job of
outlining the core principles so i'll
send that to you please please
so basically what you're doing now and
you're giving an explanation and a
justification for an appeal to try and
get people to
uh start forming the art collective that
will generate
the game what's the name of the game
again the great awakening
the great awakening right uh which but
by the way was also the name of
several uh religious revivals uh both in
england and the united states
historically
uh so right yeah that has a precedence
that way too
so um how can people
reach you get involved join
like what do you want like what
needs to happen next well i'll
leave uh my email also my website has a
contact form that you can contact me
from there as well i've got to do some
building for like more of an online
infrastructure to give
and broadcast information about this but
for now email or
contacting me through the website is uh
perfect
i mean it's strikes me that now is
actually a very good time for many
people
uh since covet has shifted schedules
around
a lot for a lot of yeah
yeah it's been a blessing and a curse
you know it's given me a lot of time to
like work on a lot of music production
to work on this book
and to also uh kind of conceive this
project it's been kind of nice although
i i
definitely am finding i'm yearning for
that more collective kind of experience
sure sure so is there anything else you
want to talk about in connection
on with these two projects i mean you've
been very eloquent so far
we can talk about literally anything um
like this project is the culmination of
basically all of the research all of the
study that i've been doing so
um i don't know where do you want to
take it i mean we could talk about
mystical experiences the spiritual
dimension of experience
but they might be more practical and i'm
worried about those questions being
premature because of the stage you're at
so if i ask them don't don't feel that
you're you're obligated to have an
answer right now
right uh so you know one of my questions
will white
what might be what do you do when people
have various
mystical experiences uh and because
people have variation in that
uh how is that going to be integrated
into what's happening to them
how are you going to help people
distinguish between
you know mystical experiences and
perhaps psychotic experiences
or other kinds of breakdown issues um
there's that concern uh you know we
don't
i would not want to be involved in
creating
yet another game that contributes to the
virtual exodus from reality
right right uh and so what what would be
the constraints in there that
actually so i mentioned talk and tolkien
has the recovery theory where he
distinguishes between good and bad
fantasy in terms of recovery
bad fantasy is escapist right good
fantasy is you go there you go through
something like an
anthropological experience to become
enculturated in that other
world so that when you return to this
one you see it in a new way
the point is to recover this world
through the augmentation of
the fantasy world and i think that what
you're proposing is of course this
the second not the escapist first
because we have lots of escapist games
we have lots of them and they're
proliferating and they're actually being
quite destructive of individual and
collective lives
so my concern would be how to structure
this so that it doesn't become escapist
instead how it how it affords recovery
so the framing of the game just
inherently
promotes that kind of um return to the
natural world
um and this kind of recovery of not only
meaning but also of active
agent-oriented participation right
because the whole premise is that
the world around you is kind of messed
up for a lot of reasons and we can
relate to the way in which it's messed
up by articulating it as this kind of
person technic
who has this kind of power and force
over the world
and then the school the academy is put
into direct
opposition um collaboration
participation with that reality
so the whole point of the game is to
grapple with things that are happening
in the here and now right excellent so
that will be a strong thematic thing
throughout all of the game so that
people yeah
yeah and what i really want to do is i
want to like be able to facilitate
um perspectival shifts so that even when
somebody's not actively in a game
scenario just out in the world
they can see an advertisement or see a
business or
you know they're searching on amazon one
day and maybe they're like oh my god i
can really see how this is sort of
you know bound to this entity technic
right um i want to be able to shift
these kinds of uh promote these kinds of
shifts in perspective
in the everyday world excellent
so how would you also
keep it symbolic and metaphoric so
people don't generate just yet another
wacky conspiracy theory out of all of
this yeah
so i mean the conspiratorial aspect is
kind of
great like it's it's a little bit
tongue-in-cheek
right because you're participating in a
secret society and right now
in the cultural mind there's a lot of
talk about secret societies and how
they're like
manipulating reality right there's this
narrative where obama created the
coronavirus as part of a democratic
communist takeover
none of this really makes any like good
rational sense you know
i mean sure maybe there are some
nefarious things happening with the the
coronavirus but like
i don't know the the whole narrative
where it's webbed into this thing where
america is the prime actor in all global
affairs and so therefore we need to vote
for donald trump
that seems a little bit like the wrong
kind of way to go
you know um so what i really want this
game to do is to be able to
capture and interface with these
tendencies that people have towards
conspiratorial thinking to allow for a
more
healthy avenue and arena for expression
so you're trying to trigger but you're
trying to trigger that machinery but
exact it
uh for uh uh uh for the training of
wisdom basically
yeah yeah like there's a need that's
being unmet in people which is
promoting them making meaning according
to these maladaptive
schemas right because i would say that
the embodied relationship of like
voting for somebody who is like an
incoherent and possibly fascist mess
that's not like a great relationship to
take to reality and those beliefs
are promoting that relationship to
reality they're promoting that action
and if you look at how global affairs
have been in the last
like 50 years you know we have been
far removed from a world that is built
on truth
everything is show everything is theater
right this is an explicit part of
um the conservative ethos i remember you
know back when there was another wave of
this
um worry about sort of fascism
especially in the united states
um there was a lot of talk about the
post-truth world and how
what people perceive is a lot more
important than what actually is the case
and so a lot of political actors and a
lot of news sources will attempt to
broadcast information warped into this
kind of narrative that promotes an
action
in their favor as opposed to actually
broadcasting and demonstrating truth
this has also been very common in russia
i was watching a documentary with my
roommates
just the other day and i learned that
one of putin's
right hand guys is he comes from
absurdist theater
and so he has made the political arena
an absurdist theater act
trying to constantly destabilize
people's perceptions
and to do that he stages protests he
uses like secret service money
in russia to fund entire opposition
parties
um different human rights movements that
like
um harass the president and everything
and then after a while he came out and
was like yes this is what i'm doing i've
basically just been paying everybody to
like
you know have these political conflicts
and now nobody knows what the hell to do
right right right
and so there's and they don't know what
to do because they don't know what's
real they don't know what to act on they
don't know what
propositions what beliefs to use as a
way to inform their relationship
to reality um and so that just allows
the the powers
that be to push their agendas uh and to
have minimal opposition in that fact
and while it's very clear to see that
happening in russia i think it's also
very clear to see that happening in the
united states which of course
influences how we do things in canada
right right
and so the idea again is um
the kind of the way a parable may looks
like it's making use of narrative
but then undermines it from within that
narrative
uh uh you know that that
narrative habit and so what you're
trying to do is sort of trigger a lot of
these habits
but undermine them within so you get
well a great awakening so people start
to awaken
towards an orientation towards one of
the
sort of central features i argued for
wisdom by socrates which is
to recouple what you find salient
to your seeking of what is true and most
real
yeah absolutely and i'm glad that you
brought up socrates here because i've
been thinking
um in terms of so in in the book that
we're writing
one of the things that's really
important is the distinction between
different theories of knowledge
right so we have the correspondence
theory and the conformity theory right
right
so i think that both of those are true i
think that the conformity theory is the
foundation for knowledge
the uh the embodied relationship that an
organism takes to its
environment which promotes its continued
existence
um that is the organism knowing its
environment by conforming to it
yes exactly participatory knowing yeah
yeah and so like most of the kinds of
knowing that we have are like that i
think participatory
um perspectival and even procedural
knowledge
are about conformity yeah yeah whereas
the propositions that's the
very small slice of knowledge it's like
the after effect of just like this
massive
neural output that's when you finally
get propositions it's like the crust
on top of how we know reality yeah
that's where coherence and
correspondence come out as more crucial
yeah yeah so in relation to socrates
i've been thinking about
his propositions of you know claiming to
not really know anything
and i was thinking hmm that makes a lot
of sense if you think about that in
terms of the embodied relationship
if you act as if you know nothing i
think that you're much more likely to
have a pro-social and adaptive
relationship with reality one that
allows you to
change your frame in an ongoing way to
pick up on the nuance of the present
moment
right if you're too dogmatic about a
proposition matt acts as
a kind of bayesian filter which makes
unlikely things that you don't expect
right if you think that this proposition
is always true
it's going to impair how you're updating
your beliefs because maybe in one
context it isn't and i think that that's
like actually a pretty good lesson for
how to deal with the
weird situation that we have now where
there's a lot of conspiratorial
narratives there's a lot of genuinely
fake news we don't really know what to
do about it
um there's a lot of propaganda out there
so
as opposed to trying to orient ourselves
towards knowing deeply what is
propositionally true
i think that if we followed that
socratic method and acted as if we don't
really
know but we're just trying to have the
best kind of relationship
um with reality uh knowing what to care
about right
the one thing that socrates did claim to
know i think that's a pretty good lesson
that
could be taken up to mitigate some of
the harms of the
current narrative chaos that we're
situated in
so the kind of play is not only a
serious play it's
it's socratically serious play right
and and you of course there's a there is
a huge element of playfulness within
uh socrates uh performance within the
dialogues
there's a lot of a lot of play in there
but that's interesting
i like that that's very it's very
interesting uh way of bringing it in
so what's what's sort of the i mean this
is probably
this is definitely a premature question
so i take it that you can answer it very
vaguely and schematically
but what's sort of the timeline you see
for this
i would love to be able to run the first
rendition of this next spring summer
right
that's great wow that's really cool
yeah it's gonna be a lot of work which
is why i need to like you know get it
out there that i need help and i need to
like build a collective of people to
help
because like i don't know i've done a
lot of organizing but i tend to
uh take on way too much work and trying
to do everything myself and i was
thinking about this project and i was
like there's no way that i could do
anything remotely like that yeah yeah i
agree i i also suffer from that the
setting sin
as well that i take out way too much um
is there anything else that
i mean i'm hoping that because you're on
with voices with raviki
you you'll be invited you should be
invited to the discord server
and i think there's like over a thousand
people there there's a very extensive
community
so you get to interact with them and be
involved with them they'll have
a live q a with you um so that's one way
of also helping you
get it out i'll promote this video of
course on my platform
is there anything else i could do to
help um
you know i feel like we could talk about
that stuff um
in the in the after math of the video um
i'm really interested in talking about
some of the more specifics
uh theoretically um i'd like to have
people
have a good thorough understanding of
like where i'm coming from what i'm
trying to achieve
um and we can also bring in some of the
stuff about the book as well because
that's basically the foundational
document
that's really helping me uh orient my
uh implementation of this project well
there's a way i can bring the practical
and the theoretical together then on
the question do you think it'd be
possible uh to coordinate the release
of the great awakening with the book
because they would probably therefore
mutually afford each other
yeah that's that's possible let me think
about that
hmm
my intuition right now is that i think
just because we've already done like a
crowdfunding campaign for and we have a
bunch of people waiting for it
that it might be good to get that out
there
as soon as possible um and then i think
that also just having the book available
to be read
and then telling people that there's
like a game that you can like
uh play to learn more and to have um
some more education in these concepts
i think that might be a good way to go
about it and the reverse once people
start taking up the game you can point
them to the existing book
yeah what i've been wanting to do is to
build an online course about the book
because it's a little bit dense but um i
was thinking that i could just have that
course be a part of that game
oh that's cool that's cool so this game
will take a long time to play you said
about three months
yeah at least that yeah how much per day
would people be committing time uh
that's a good question i'm thinking of
something along the lines of like
like a part-time uh university course
load
so maybe like 10 to 15 hours a week
something like that so
it's you got to really set the time
aside but
you know the more the more you give the
more you get out of it of course
like any good game so now up back to a
more theoretical
level um tonight on peter lindberg's
estoa i'm going to be talking with james
cars
who wrote the religious case against
belief but more relevant right now
he wrote a book that on reading called
finite and infinite games and he
distinguishes between trying to play a
finite game
and trying to play an infinite game the
the goal of the finite game is to end
the game so no so nobody can play it
anymore by having somebody declared
and entitled as the winner whereas the
point of the infinite game
is to figure out how to constantly you
know adjust
and modify the rules so that the game
can
continue to be played over and over
again i'm very interested in this
distinction because
i see debate as a finite game but i see
via logos
as an infinite game and trying to figure
out and therefore the way we
do debate should not be the way in which
we try to do via logos
you can incorporate smaller finite games
as moves within an infinite game
but they always have to be encompassed
within um the larger
uh project of maintaining play
um and there and so no one is seeking
um to be entitled so obviously the
finite game is much more in metallic
mode
and the infinite game is much more
peritolic etc
so it sounds to me like one of the
things you're trying to do
also is to take people who are used to
playing
finite games virtual games and
educate them in how to play an infinite
game
which is the love of wisdom because we
never become
gods we are always in the infinite game
of
trying to become more and more like the
gods to use a socratic model
yeah yeah that sounds exactly like what
i'm trying to achieve
within the neoplatonic framework um you
know theosis is one of the
the primary goals becoming godlike
and so that's very much informing how
i'm structuring this game and it is very
much an infinite game because there are
certain perennial problems that
spirituality is intended to solve
our tendency towards self-deception yeah
a tendency towards nihilism
you know all of those things and so
those things are never going to go away
so you have to have an ongoing game that
can consistently interface with these to
mitigate these perennial problems
perennially
so it sounds like therefore people might
play the game
multiple times um yeah yeah
i want to be able to change it as it
goes um
so the game that i'm developing right
now is very much tailored towards the
needs of the current
culture but as the needs of the culture
change then there will be different
scenarios that can
meet those needs excellent excellent
there's also like a permanent community
that you get initiated into
so once you go through a round of the
game then you
sort of graduate you get like a degree
in the game and you're a part of that
community
kind of similar to like a freemason
degree and then you sort of unlock new
capacities so there'll be certain
member-only events that you can go to
i want to have like a big yearly party
where this alternate timeline phases in
and you can like hang out with these
alien beings for a little bit
um this constant festival this return to
this other reality
so it'll be something that's ongoing
that is mutable that changes
that allows ongoing participation to
meet the needs of the
current time perhaps the that that
community will also be a reservoir of
distributed cognition
for updating and revising the game yeah
yeah what i want to do is i want to have
that
people who graduate the game i want that
to be the
um hiring pool ah right right
that's cool that's very very cool yeah
so if this grows large enough um
which i hope it does i'd like to be like
a very
large and comprehensive media production
thing as well um and i'd like to have
members who have gone through the game
uh be the primary people who get hired
to
work on projects and like way down the
line you know
the the current narrative apparatus of
our current society you know the
studios of hollywood and disney all of
these people that um
create and sustain our perceptions and
determine what
archetypal symbolic narratives are
activated in us
these institutions are doing these
things because they want our capital and
i think we would be
foolish to think that the stories aren't
influenced
at the end of the day only by that which
will maximize capital
and so i'd like to have a system of
media production of um
you know movies comic books something
like a marvel universe
within this um cosmic narrative
that can be broadcast out to people but
then there's this central mystery school
that if you want to learn certain core
truths within this extended uh universe
uh you go and you participate in the
game to like really get the full
depth that's being hinted at in all of
these narratives that are happening in
this alternate timeline
so kind of like neoplatonic christianity
then
yeah yeah it's very much similar to that
sort of um sacramental liturgical
kind of lifestyle which you see being
reenacted by things like um
cosplay culture and the marvel universe
like people desperately want to
live in these kinds of immersive
universes yes very much
right that's that's very good
that's very good i'm wondering if
there's a connection between
playing finite games and seeking escape
and playing infinite games and seeking
recovery
that's something that's that's worth
sort of reflecting on and trying to draw
out
what i what comes to mind first when i
think of that is something like call of
duty or
modern warfare which is a finite game
that you can infinitely play
it's something that is simple enough
that you can have your attention be
yoked to it for you know hours days
years but it does have this winner loser
structure
so it's very much a finite game you
could put it down and leave afterwards
but very often people
attempt to um infinitely replicate their
experience with this game i think league
of legends is one of those games that's
like notorious for this for sucking
people's attention in
right right right right so i think maybe
there could be like a modal confusion
thing happening where
the attempt to um escape to the
finite game infinitely is more a symptom
of this mass exodus
yeah yeah that's well put i like that i
like that as a way of responding to my
question i think that's very good
i like that so what about people
who have established religious
traditions
um uh do you think they'd want to play
this game
um i hope so
you know as as as you do as well i try
to be as respectful as possible to
all kinds of religious philosophies
and you know sometimes that goes well
sometimes it doesn't well
let me let me tell you there's a little
bit more behind my question i i am
influenced by verse lewis's argument
that neoplatonism is sort of the grammar
of the spirituality
of the west you know of the of the
mystical traditions within christianity
within islam within judaism and degree
to which i think you're trying to plug
into that grammar
might afford people from different
faiths being able to
participate in the game cooperatively
and even commune together through it
yeah i think that's about right i mean
neoplatonism i i agree with that thesis
and i i'm definitely
deeply influenced by that myself and
it's what i'm trying to implement here
so
i think that shared cognitive grammar
will be something that people can
readily
attach to i also think the fact that um
i'm trying to re-initiate people into
a world based on the ideas of life
and music also is helpful in that
project because that is the world in
which
these uh older traditions are situated
right that's much more amenable to a
christian world than is this mechanistic
world
when we tried to fit god into that world
he died yes
yes so would part of the courses
also be the more philosophically
challenging project of taking
so i mean this is analogous to the
argument i've made about
psychotechnologies you adopt them for
certain reasons and then they permeate
and then you end up being exacted your
cognition gets accepted
and then your your your experience
changes and then you come up with a new
metaphysics
to try and make sense of that change
like the axial revolution or something
like that right
is it going to be like you're inducing
you're going to be inducing all this in
people uh but there's still the
very difficult project which not
everybody has to undertake
i acknowledge that right now but some
people will need to and some people will
want to
undertake the project the philosophical
project of okay i have this
and then here is the this mechanistic
worldview that is
still wrapped up in science and certain
models
the philosophical project of trying to
integrate and bridge between them
seems like something that some people
are going to want to pursue after
playing the great awakening
that is something that i want to work on
as well
so with these world views i think that
we
would do well to recognize them as
models as opposed to what reality
actually
is i think that this search to need to
know
certainly what the stuff of being is is
kind of a confused search
we are i think always kind of at a
remove
from phenomena we are always translating
being
into a way that makes sense to us and by
doing that we are abstracting it
so it it's not that the cosmos is
literally
like an organism or that the cosmos is
literally like the machine
but we can utilize different ways of
relating to reality and understanding it
uh to articulate it in those terms and
then to act on it
according to what those terms motivates
us
to do right so what i really like is
this object-oriented ontology framework
which is also built into this sort of
hydagarian view of
um nature and like the the relationship
to nature and so
within object or objected oriented
ontology um
it articulates all objects as
similar to like the medieval view of
like these um
inherent substances that are kind of
beyond phenomena there's this little
kernel of ineffability in everything
there's always going to be something
that we can't grasp
and so what we're tasked with doing is
establishing a relationship
with that which we simply cannot know
literally and so we have
options we have the model of life
or we have the model of mechanism and
these actually map
fairly well on to um right and left
hemispheric processing right so if you
look at the work of
uh ian mcgill christ mastering emissary
he goes on at length to talk about how
the implicit intuitive effective
processes that are more common to the
right hemisphere
promote a relationship to reality which
is more like a relationship between
a lived being and another lived being
yes yes
and then with the left side which has
all of your language articulation
functions
that is much more heavily involved in
tool use and tool manipulation so these
two modes of uh
life and lived relationship versus
manipulation and mechanism
map onto very basic neural cognitive
parameters that we're never really going
to get out of
so reality is always going to be
something in between these two modes and
we have to be able to learn to oscillate
between them flexibly
and to learn when one provides the
optimal relationship in this situation
and when the other one does
right and so educating people in the
fact that
how we understand reality is always
about the participatory relationship
with it
and that these explicit modes are tools
that we can employ
i think that that will do wonders to um
facilitate this integration of these
modes and in line with mcgill chris
i do think that it's correct to say that
because
of the um sorts of things that are being
processed by these
hemispheric areas that that should be
the master and the other should be the
emissary
yeah i you probably know that some of
the viewers will know
i had a really wonderful conversation
with ian um
on rebel wisdom i hope to have another
one in the future um
yeah i i think that's very well said um
and i sort of i think of wisdom as what
you're talking about
what it what one of the things wisdom
should function to do is optimize the
relationship between
the left and right uh uh hemispheric
ways of
of of of constituting the agent arena
relationship
and and that's why i think insight is
such an important phenomenon because
insight is a moment
of reconfiguration where you get at
least a momentary optimization between
the right and the left hemispheres and
that's why i think
insight is such a central feature of
wisdom
so the game should be very insight
provoking i hope
yeah yeah absolutely insight provoking
and also giving people the explicit
tools
to make sense of um the insights that
are being evoked exactly
exactly always you need both
okay well um that's about our time
um is there anything you'd like to say
something i think
daniel this was you were you were
extremely like just bang on today it was
very eloquent uh very rich um very
flowing
and highly enjoyable um but i'd like to
give you sort of
the last word yeah um
let me see geez i feel like i can tell
that i was very flowy today because like
it feels like it's been like 10 minutes
you know
uh let me see oh god what do i what's
the last thing that i want to leave
people with
hmm
oh yeah i'm kind of at an impasse let me
what's coming to me right now is this
quote i've been reading a book on
krishna so i think i might just want to
like
read this quote and then expand on it
for like a minute okay
it has to do with the importance of play
and one thing that i i didn't know is
that
the story of krishna is called the
divine play and the metaphor of game and
theater is saturated throughout the
story
oh yeah so it's really interesting so
he's born at a time of maximal
wickedness
and his role is to introduce like
playfulness
into reality and that playfulness is
what helps to
alleviate the wickedness of men to
overthrow the demon king
um so it's it's really interesting
because usually you have these kinds of
like cosmic god
narratives and it's like very serious
right even like the christ story krishna
and christ have a lot in common
um but you know christ goes through this
drama where he's like murdered and it's
very dramatic but for krishna he like
you know steals butter and he plays
music and he's like a playful little kid
right right let me just where is it here
uh yes so this is um i think a prayer to
krishna
hail to the divine child who has taken
on a forum for sport
seeing his playful exploits even the
minds of the sirius will be swayed
may that may that playful form lead me
to the end of the game of life
and i i've noticed that for people that
i know who have
become deeply involved in in spiritual
experiences utilizing psychedelic
medicines and so on
it's really interesting how frequently
people come to the insight that life is
like a game
but i think you know some people will
claim life is literally a game my soul
chose to be
incarnated in this arena for particular
game purposes
but i think that if we understand that
as an embodied participatory
relationship it is genuinely the case
that life is better live
if it's understood as a game right right
and this seriousness you know clinging
to things clinging to
my truth what i want what i think needs
to happen
those are the kinds of things that
promote suffering and promote
actions that cause very physical harm
and suffering
so i'm really looking forward to trying
to introduce a little bit of playfulness
to embody that krsna's spirit
um to sway the minds of the sirius with
a little bit of play because i think
that's what we all really need
especially right now you know the
world's been very serious
for the whole of 2020. it's kind of hard
i'm emotionally struggling as a result
of it and i know many people are as well
and i think that a little bit of play in
our lives will go a long way to
helping us all live better well thank
you daniel i
i take it though you you don't mean that
that play is just frivolous
or the goal is just fun oh no it is
an incarnation of the energy of vishnu
the sustainer and preserver of life
okay that sounds like an excellent place
uh
to end it uh so so thank you very very
much
it's been wonderful thank you daniel and
thank you